Well, hey there and welcome to unit two
of a push. Now, in this video, I reckon
we ought to cinch up our comparison
pants and consider how various European
colonial empires developed. And we're
going to consider the Spanish and the
French and the Dutch and then finally
the British. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
So, here's the big idea for this whole
video. Power, partnership, and
partition. And I reckon I was explaining
that up for you. So, we got four
imperial powers that we're going to
spend some time with. You got Spain, and
then the French and Dutch, which we're
going to consider together as a unit,
and then the British. Okay. So all four
of these powers pursued and built
colonial empires in the Americas, but
they all looked quite different. And
that's mainly owing to the fact that
each power deployed different tactics to
achieve their colonial goals. And in
general, their chief goal toward which
all their colonizing tactics were aimed
was economic prosperity. Now, Spain saw
colonial wealth through power and
control over indigenous peoples. The
French and Dutch saw colonial wealth
through partnership with indigenous
people. And the British sought wealth by
partitioning or separating themselves
from indigenous people. And so while all
three powers basically wanted the same
thing, namely a nasty payday, their
tactics to reach that goal varied. And
that meant that each empire looked and
felt a lot different from the others.
Okay, big idea unlocked. And now let's
spend some time in the details of each
colonial empire. But hold on just a
second. Hey, come closer. Let me get a
look at you. Yeah. Yeah, I knew it. I
know you're the kind of student who
wants to get an A in your class and a
five on your exam in May. And if I'm
right, then baby, I got something for
you. This is my A Push Heimler review
guide, and it has everything you need to
study as fast as possible. It's got
exclusive whole unit review videos that
you're not going to see here on YouTube.
It's got note guides to follow along,
practice multiple choice questions for
each unit, full length practice exams,
and answer keys for every dang bit of
it. So, if that's the kind of help you
need, then get that clicky finger out
and check the link in the description.
Okay, so let's start with Spain and
consider what made their colonial empire
in the Americas different from the other
European powers. Spain's main goal in
establishing colonies in the Americas
was to extract wealth, first in the form
of minerals like gold and silver, and
over time through the export of cash
crops using enslaved labor. And so in
order to get the boom boom they desired,
the Spanish rolled up to the Americas
with a fistful of raw authoritarian
power, which is to say they wanted to be
all the way in charge of everybody's
crap. And those tactics led them to
create certain institutions to help them
achieve that goal. Now the first tactic
was the subjugation of native
populations. And I'm going to give you
two examples. First, you have the encoma
system, which we talked about in the
last unit. But by way of reminder,
incomando was a system in which the
Spanish crown granted an encomando
authority over attractive land. And the
indigenous people living on that land
were compelled by force to extract
wealth from the land either through
mining or farming or sometimes you know
both. And then in return for that labor
the encomando was responsible for
protecting the indigenous people and
trying to convert them to Christianity.
Now all this is just fancy language to
say that incomi enda amounted to slavery
and all the brutality that comes with
that institution. However, in 1542, the
Spanish crown enacted what became known
as the new laws in an attempt to curb
the power of those rascally encomandos
and to mitigate the harsh treatment of
indigenous workers. These laws were
passed thanks to a growing contingent of
Spanish reformers. Our boy Bartome de
lascas chief among them who wanted the
encomandanda system to pass away. And
despite some significant rebellions
against those laws from recalcitrant and
commanderos, the new laws led to the
decline of this particular form of
slavery. But hey, you didn't think the
Spanish weren't going to come up with
another coerced labor system they could
use to extract wealth from the Americas,
did you? Don't be crazy. No, it came to
replacing commando was known as hienda.
Although to be clear, both systems did
kind of coexist at the same time. But
after the passage of the new laws,
hienda became the main Spanish labor
system in the Americas. Now, the
difference between these two systems is
subtle, but it is important. The whole
idea of encoma is that Spain granted
land to encomandos who then forced
indigenous people to work in return for
protecting and Christianizing them. And
big point of emphasis here in
Encomienda, the Encomanderos did not own
the land. But in the Hienda system,
Encomanderos did own large tracks of
land and the indigenous people living on
them were not technically enslaved.
However, the laborers were kind of tied
to the land in a debt repayment system.
So, you know, still kind of a coerced
labor system. Okay. Now, the second
tactic Spain used to assert power and
dominate their colonial holdings was by
attempting to convert the natives to
Christianity. For example, after Spanish
explorer Don Juan Deonate brutally
subdued the Pueeblo people in the Great
Plains region, he established the
capital of Santa Fe and the missionaries
came behind to set up what was known as
the mission system. Now, at first, some
people who did adopt Christianity by
adding Christ to their own pantheon of
gods. But the priest got real saucy
about this on account of a key doctrine
of Christianity is that there is only
one God and that one God does not abide
company. So when the Spanish priests
refused to allow Pueblo people to adapt
Christianity to their own way of
understanding the world, what they were
really doing was attempting to erase and
redefine their entire culture. And so
eventually the Pueblo grew tired of this
coercion and rebelled in the Pueblo
revolt of 1680. They killed hundreds of
Spaniards and destroyed every church in
the area and reestablished their own
cultural customs. However, the Spanish
did return a few years later and
reasserted their dominance. Why, says
you? Well, says I. Because they were all
about power and domination. However, to
be fair, when the Spanish did return to
this area, they kind of chilled out a
little bit toward the Pueblo as far as
religious rigidity goes, but you know,
the point still stands. And finally, the
third tactic the Spanish used to create
their colonial empire was the creation
of a new social order known as the cast
system. This system created a social
hierarchy in which a person's place in
society was determined by the amount of
white blood they had. And to put it
mildly, this got complicated, y'all. So,
obviously, the pure-blooded Spanish
themselves were at the top of the
hierarchy. And not surprisingly, the
pure African and indigenous peoples were
at the bottom. But in the middle there
were something like 40 different
categories that were the result of the
Spanish and the indigenous peoples and
the Africans mixing together creating
what the Spanish deemed as new races. So
in some the Spanish wanted wealth out of
the new world and their main tactic to
get it was authoritarian power. Now
compared to the Spanish, the French and
Dutch had relatively few colonists in
the new world. And whereas the Spanish
made use of power, the French and Dutch
tactics were better described as
partnership with the indigenous peoples.
So let's start with the French. It was
Samuel de Champlain who founded the
first permanent French settlement at
Quebec in6008. Now, France was a little
late to the game because they were
distracted with a bunch of wars in
Europe and they were busy oppressing
their Protestant population known as the
Hugeno. And that was important word
because, as you may or may not know, the
Hugeno don't oppress themselves. Anyway,
the French emphasis in the Americas was
not on establishing permanent
settlements, but rather on growing
wealthy through trade partnerships with
the various indigenous people groups,
especially the fur trade. As an example
of this partnership mindset and
establishing Quebec, Desan Plain
negotiated alliances with the Huron
people in the St. Lawrence River Valley
against their traditional enemies, the
Hodeni. And if you recall, that's a lot
different than the way the Spanish
interacted with indigenous people. Now,
one of the biggest deals for the French
in the New World was the beaver fur
trade. By allying with American Indian
groups, as well as intermaring with
them, French fur trappers were able to
satisfy the growing demand among the
French elite for this precious item. And
the French did send missionaries to the
New World just like the Spanish did, but
they made very few converts since they
didn't make use of brute force as the
Spanish did. However, several French
missionaries did prove vital as
explorers and cgraphers for the French
colonial cause. And then real similar to
the French were the Dutch. In6009, the
Dutch sent Henry Hudson to explore North
America, looking for a northwest passage
through the Americas to Asia. As it
turns out, that passage did not exist
except way up in the Arctic Circle. But
Hudson did explore other regions and
ended up establishing the colony of New
Amsterdam. Now, just like every other
imperial power, the Dutch did all this
cuz they wanted the boom boom. But
unlike the Spanish, the Dutch were not
interested in remaking indigenous
societies into their own image. Although
they did form alliances with the
Irakcoy. As a result, New Amsterdam
became a significant and busy trading
port which attracted merchants from all
over the world. In fact, one account
says that more than a dozen languages
could be heard spoken in the streets.
And that's because in some the French
and Dutch mainly used the tactic of
partnership in establishing their new
world empire. Okay, slap yourself in the
face and wake up because it's time to
consider our last imperial state, namely
the British. Okay, compared to the other
European powers, way more people,
including whole families, came from
Great Britain to settle in North
America. And the main tactic they used
was partition, which means they sought
to separate themselves from the
indigenous people. And wouldn't you know
it, that tactic led to the creation of a
colonial empire that looked a lot
different from other imperial powers in
the new world. Now, the British
certainly had profits on the mind when
it came to establishing their colonies
in the Americas. But in general, the
migrants who came from Britain came to
the Americas for four basic reasons.
First, migrants came seeking economic
prosperity, just like the other powers.
So, for example, the first British
colony established was James Town
in6007, and it was mostly populated by
single young men looking to strike it
rich by extracting gold. Now, as it
turned out, there wasn't much gold in
that region. And since they didn't see
much point in planting crops or anything
that they needed to survive, many of
them starved that first year. And it
wasn't until later when the colony
started focusing on the export of
tobacco that the wealth really started
flowing in. But we'll talk more about
that in another video. The point is in
establishing this colony, the British
did their best to throw up a thick wall
of separation between themselves and the
indigenous people living there because,
you know, partition. Now, second, the
British came seeking social mobility. It
turns out there was only so much social
XP to be earned back in Britain, what
with all of its entrenched systems of
nobility and whatnot. Additionally, a
series of primogenature laws dictated
that only the oldest son could legally
inherit land. And that meant that
younger brothers who had some social
ambition looked to the new world for
land and better social standing. And so
once joint stock companies became the
primary way to fund exploration, many of
these younger sons took the trip to
North America in order to acquire landed
wealth which they were denied in
England. Now third, the British came
seeking religious freedom. Now I don't
think it's too much to say that during
this period, religion in Britain was a
hot mess. You see, in the 1530s, our boy
King Henry VIII declared Great Britain
to be a Protestant state with himself as
the head of the church. However, the
Church of England retained many of the
trappings of Catholicism, and that got
some of the British Protestants more
than a little spicy. And there are two
groups you need to know, namely the
Puritans and the Separatists. Now, these
two groups had a lot in common since
they were both pretty much defined by
the Calvinist flavor of the Protestant
movement. And in general, anything that
even faintly smelled Catholic or popish
was repugnant in their nostrils. But the
difference between these two groups was
their solution to all the perceived
popery in the Anglican church. The
Puritans believed that the church could
be reformed or purified from the inside
by remaining part of it. But the
separatists believed that the church was
hopeless and therefore the true
Protestant church could only be formed
from the outside, namely by separating
from the Anglican church. Now, as is the
custom of religious reformers, these
groups gave King James the 1 a heaping
earful of their complaints and the king
got real tired of all that religious gum
flapping. So, he began putting more and
more pressure on them and eventually a
group of separatists, otherwise known as
the pilgrims, departed for the new world
with a little stop in Holland in order
to find religious freedom there. Now,
they intended to sail to Virginia, but
the ship got blown way off course and
instead they landed in Plymouth Bay and
established a new colony in 1620. They
migrated as family groups and their goal
was to establish a god- centered society
in the new world where they could
worship without harassment. And although
they accepted some help from indigenous
people in the beginning, over time, the
pilgrims attempted to live entirely
separate from them. And fourth, some
British people migrated to the new world
to seek improved living conditions. So,
at the beginning of the 17th century,
England's population was growing like
mad. And at the same time, Parliament
was passing enclosure laws that allowed
landlords to claim public lands to feed
their livestock. And that was a big
problem because this land was known as
the commons and it was available to all
people to graze their animals. It was a
vital resource to poor citizens who had
no land of their own and nowhere else to
feed their livestock. So when this land
began disappearing, more and more of
these landless poor began to migrate
from Britain to the new world in order
to improve their standard of living.
Okay, so let's sum all of this up real
quick. Spain tried to integrate
indigenous people into a new society
through the raw use of power. The French
and Dutch partnered with them for
economic benefit, but the English
partitioned or separated themselves and
sought to take the land of the natives
and keep them away with violence if
necessary. Okay, you can click here to
watch my other unit 2 videos or you can
click here to grab my A pushheimler
review guide which will help you study
as fast as possible. Now, I appreciate
you coming around and I'll catch you on
the flip-flop. I'm Lur.